All right. So, now we're going to talk
about how to generate a random number.
So, when you generate a random number,
it's not really random. Your computer is
running a whole bunch of um math on a
starting point and it gives you a number
that seems random. It's not really
random, but it's as close as we can get
in computers. So, the way you generate a
random number is you use the math
library. So to use the math library,
just like we've been doing in the last
videos, we type math and then we type
dot and then we type random.
This random and then we'll put
parenthesis. This generates a random
number between zero and.9999
repeating. So to demonstrate this, I'm
going to create a variable say let my
num equal math.random random and then
put the parenthesis and the semicolon
and then we'll just alert my null. So
we'll save this and we'll go take a look
at our web page and it put 319250
and that's the number on screen. So
we'll reload the page and now we got 018
and we'll reload the page and it's 0551.
So it's always between zero and almost
positive one. It will never include one,
but it'll get close. So, let's say you
want to generate a number, but you want
to generate a number between 0 and 10.
So, let's So, if this right here
generates a number between zero
and.9999,
if we multiply that by 10, then it'll
generate a number between 0 and 9.9999.
Um, so that could get us a random number
between zero and nine. If we multiplied
it by 11, that would give us um a number
between zero and almost 11. So um we can
take advantage of that and generate that
random number. So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to say let's take this
random number and let's multiply it by
10.
We save that and we alert my number.
We now get 8.1. And if we reload, we get
3.7. We reload, we get 3.4. Um, so we
can see it's generating random numbers,
but it has a lot of decimal places on
the end. And maybe we want to get rid of
those. If only there was a way to chop
decimal places off of a number. And
there is. Um, the way you do that is you
use what is called the floor function.
So you say math.f floor and if you put
parenthesis it takes in a number and it
returns the same number without any
decimal places. So if we put my number
when we say alert math.f floor on my
number our number can be anywhere
between zero and um 9.99999
because we're multiplying by 10.
So if we save that and we come over to
our code, we get seven. And we reload
the page and we get zero. We reload the
page and we get one. We reload the page
and we get six. So now we are generating
a random number between zero and nine
inclusive.
Well, what if we wanted it to be between
1 and 10?
Well, if we want to shift that, then we
could take the number that we've just
floored, and I'm going to take the alert
off of it.
So, the first number makes it so that we
generate a number between zero and
9.99999.
Math.floor says strip off
the decimal places. So, now we're
generating a number between zero and
nine. So if we want to be generating a
number between one and 10, all we have
to do is add one to it. Because if we
add one, if we generate the bottom of
the range, we'll generate a zero. 0 + 1
is 1. If we generate the top of the
range, uh we'll generate a 9. 9 + 1 is
10. So that'll give us a number between
0 and 10.
You can do this all on one line if you
would like. Um, and the way you do that
is you say let my random num. So you're
creating a random number. You're setting
it equal to. So you'll start by taking
math.random. That's a number between
zero and almost one.
You'll multiply it by 10. So that's a
number between 0 and 9.9999.
And then if you say math.f floor on that
number. Now
you have a number between zero and nine
because you're chopping off the decimal
places. And if you add one to it, now
you have a number random number between
1 and 10. And that concludes the video
on random numbers.